{
  "reference_number": "145",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "First we must be absolutely clear what the target actually is. We must understand the difference between short cycle carbon and long\n\n cycle carbon. The target must be for zero Long Cycle Carbon"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "This cannot be net it has to be zero. ETS is a fraud in that it cannot provide long term sequestering of Long Cycle Carbon Dioxide.\n\n The forest owners will not be throwing the trees in a swamp! With a pine tree life of 28 years on average it only offers 14 years\n sequestering. Once harvested depending on use the long cycle carbon dioxide will be returned to the atmosphere as long cycle\n carbon, just because it has been through a tree does not change this. Return times will vary from about 6 months for toilet paper to\n\n 100 years for building. There is currently no commercial long term sequestering for long cycle carbon emissions. We need to accept\n this and move on. I am all for increasing the bio mass of the planet (apart from humans) but to add this to any equation is woolly\n thinking. If we had adopted ETS immediately it was developed all of the Carbon Dioxide will have already been returned to the\n\n Atmosphere!"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Don't count on the tress see above"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "While we have already set in place 24m sea level rise in the next 2500 years or about 1m/year it will be storms or heat waves that will\n strike us first and will be the only thing that will galvanism public opinion sufficiently for more that just tokenism and more studies."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Rolling commitments will be a start but government funding wont be enough"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "They are going to do it anyway, so it will be politically naive to propose otherwise"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But as they are well outside the political cycle it will be pointless"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Education. we need to understand what we are trying to do and communicate it to all members of society, as we will need everyone's\n\nactive co-operation."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but not at the expense of actually doing things"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The ETS is a fraud and needs to be dispensed with it is not going to help us achieve our goals and will in fact delay us further. Also\nmethane emissions from agriculture, the elderly and landfills do not contribute to Long Term Climate Change. They are part of the\n\nshort carbon cycle and must be treated as such. As long as we have distractions form the real issue holding us back we will never\nmake real progress. Like food in the solid waste debate, it is a smoke screen to the real elephant in the room - Synthetics. Food is\nnot a solid waste and our grandchildren will not thank us for or food diversion efforts. Like ETS we are moving more of the tonnes\n\nonto them!"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But there must be a very high bar to minimize \"Green-washing\". Classical Sustainability is essential a fraud too, where so called\nsustainability programs are essentials \"we were slightly more sustainable than we would have been if we had not bothered\"."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes not as much the sea level change that is slow but the weather resilience."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As long as it was not green-washing and box ticking exercises which they currently are."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is already too late we are going to have to adapt to the new equilibrium's. However we have a chance of stopping it getting\nexcessively worse. The plastics in our seas will also be around for centuries and we need to help as much of our fellow Flora and\n\nFauna survive too if we can or at the end of this we will be alone."
    }
  ]
}
